A Finding Aid to the Fairfield Porter Papers, 1888-2001 (bulk 1924-1975), in the Archives of American Art AAA.portfair
Archives of American Art
Fairfield Porter papers
bulk 1924-1975
1888-2001
AAA.portfair
Archives of American Art
8.2 Linear feet
The papers of New York-based painter, lithographer, art critic, and poet Fairfield Porter measure 8.2 linear feet and date from 1888 to 2001, with the bulk of material dating from 1924 to 1975. Papers document Porter's life and career through correspondence, writings, business records, printed materials, photographs, and artwork.
Porter, Fairfield
Biographical Note
Fairfield Porter was born near Chicago in 1907, the fourth of five children of James and Ruth Furness Porter. His father was an architect, his mother a poet from a literary family, and Porter grew up in an environment where art and literature were highly valued. His father designed the family homes in Winnetka, Illinois and on Great Spruce Head Island, an island in Maine that he purchased for the family in 1912. Fairfield Porter spent summers there from the age of six, and views of the island, its structures, and neighboring towns were the subjects of many paintings.
Porter attended Harvard from 1924 to 1928, studying fine art with Arthur Pope and philosophy with Alfred North Whitehead. After graduating from Harvard, Porter moved to New York City and took studio classes at the Art Students League from 1928 until 1930, studying with Boardman Robinson and Thomas Hart Benton, and immersing himself in the art and radical politics of Greenwich Village. In the 1940s, he studied at Parson's School of Design with art restorer Jacques Maroger, adopting the Maroger recipe for an oil medium in his own painting.
To further his education as an artist, Porter traveled to Europe in 1931, where he spent time with expatriate art theorist Bernard Berenson and his circle. When he returned to New York, he allied himself with progressive, socialist organizations, and like many of his contemporaries, worked at creating socially relevant art. He did artwork for the John Reed Club, a communist group; taught drawing classes for Rebel Arts, a socialist arts organization; wrote for their magazine, Arise!; and created a mural for the Queens branch of the Socialist Party. Living in the Chicago area for several years in the 1930s, he illustrated chapbooks for the socialist poet John Wheelwright's Poems for a Dime and Poems for Two Bits series. Porter's financial contributions to the radical Chicago publication Living Marxism kept it afloat for several years.
In 1932, Porter married Anne Channing, a poet from Boston, and they settled in New York. The Porters had five children, and their first son, born in 1934, suffered from a severe form of autism. In the next decade, they had two more sons, and spent three years in Porter's hometown of Winnetka, where he had his first solo exhibition of paintings. When they returned to New York in 1939, the Porters became friends with Edwin Denby, Rudy Burkhardt, and Elaine and Willem de Kooning. Porter became an earnest admirer of Willem de Kooning's artwork and was among the first to review and purchase it.
In 1949, the Porters moved to the small, seaside town of Southampton, New York. Their two daughters were born in 1950 and 1956. Like the family home on Great Spruce Head Island, Southampton became the setting of many of Porter's paintings. In fact, almost all of his mature paintings depict family homes, surrounding landscapes, family members, and friends. Porter was an individualistic painter who embraced figurative art in the late 1940s and 1950s, when abstract expressionism was the prevailing aesthetic trend. Porter once made a comment that his commitment to figurative painting was made just to spite art critic Clement Greenberg, a respected critic and ideologue who had championed abstract expressionism and denigrated realism as passé.
Porter established his reputation as a painter and as a writer in the 1950s. John Bernard Myers of the vanguard Tibor de Nagy gallery gave Porter his first New York exhibition in 1951 and represented him for the next twenty years. That same year Tom Hess, editor of ArtNews, hired Porter to write art features and reviews. Porter went on to contribute to ArtNews until 1967 and also became art editor for The Nation beginning in 1959, the same year his article on Willem de Kooning won the Longview Foundation Award in art criticism. As a critic, Porter visited countless galleries and studios, and he gained a reputation for writing about art with the understanding and vested interest of an artist, and with the same independence from fashionable ideas that he demonstrated in his artwork.
The 1950s and 1960s were prolific years for Porter's writing and art, and saw the development of his critical ideas and the maturation of his painting. Porter enjoyed an elder status among a circle of younger artists such as Jane Freilicher, Larry Rivers, and Alex Katz, and their many poet friends, now known as the New York School of Poetry: Frank O'Hara, John Ashbery, James Schuyler, Kenneth Koch, Barbara Guest, and others. Porter himself wrote poetry and was published in the 1950s, sometimes alongside poems by his wife, who had been publishing poetry since the 1930s (twice in the vanguard Chicago journal, Poetry). The Porters' correspondence is laced with poems they and their friends sent back and forth, often about and dedicated to each other.
Besides his annual exhibitions at Tibor de Nagy and later Hirschl and Adler Galleries, Porter exhibited regularly at the Whitney, and had one-man exhibitions at many museums including the Rhode Island School of Design (1959), The University of Alabama (1963), Cleveland Museum of Art (his first retrospective, 1966), Trinity College (1967), the Parrish Art Museum (1971), the Maryland Institute of Art (1973), and the 1968 Venice Biennale. He also had residencies at the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture (1964) and Amherst College (1969). Porter died in 1975 at age 68. A full-scale retrospective of his artwork was held at the Boston Museum of Fine Art, Boston in 1983, and a study center and permanent home for his artwork was established at the Parrish Art Museum in Southampton through a donation made by Anne Porter. A posthumous collection of his poems was published by Tibor de Nagy Editions in 1985, and a catalogue raisonnée, edited by Joan Ludman, was published in 2001.
This biography relies heavily on information found in Justin Spring's biography of Porter, Fairfield Porter: A Life in Art (Yale University Press, 2000).
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York-based painter, lithographer, art critic, and poet Fairfield Porter measure 8.2 linear feet and date from 1888 to 2001, with the bulk of material dating from 1924 to 1975. The collection includes a biographical chronology; certificates, awards, and diplomas; letters to Fairfield and Anne Porter; scattered outgoing correspondence; and reviews, essays, notes, poems, and translations written by Porter and others. Among the writings are poetry manuscripts written by several New York School Poets including Frank O'Hara, James Schuyler, and Kenneth Koch. Also found are gallery records, inventories and appraisals, financial records, exhibition catalogs, clippings, posters, and records of Anne Porter's efforts to place his collection and document and publish his work after his death. Photographs of Porter, his homes, and his family are also present, as well as sketchbooks, loose sketches, and drawings spanning his entire career.
Significant correspondence is present from the Porters' many poet friends, including Kenneth Koch, James Schuyler, Ron Padgett, Kenward Elmslie, Barbara Guest, Carl Morse, David Shapiro, and others. Among the letters are poetry manuscripts by Koch, Morse, Schuyler, Padgett, and Shapiro. Some letters are actually written in verse, especially those from Kenneth Koch.
Artists with letters in the collection include Joe Brainard, Rudy Burkhardt, John Button, Lucien Day, Rackstraw Downes, Philip Evergood, Jane Frielicher, Arthur Giardelli, Leon Hartl, Alex Katz, Edward Laning, Roy Lichtenstein, Larry Rivers, Richard Stankiewicz, Nicolas Vasilieff, among others. Other art world figures represented include John Bernard Myers, curator at the Tibor de Nagy gallery (New York), and Tom Hess, editor of ArtNews. Artwork found within the correspondence includes an illustrated letter from Ron Padgett and an original print on a holiday card by Edith Schloss.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following nine series. See the series descriptions below for more information about the content of each series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1916-1975 (Box 1 and 11; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1918-1996 (Boxes 1-2; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings by Fairfield Porter, 1924-1975 (Box 2; 0.6)
Series 4: Writings by Others, 1888-1992 (Boxes 2-3; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 5: Personal Business Records, 1944-1996 (Boxes 3-4; 1 linear foot)
Series 6: Anne Porter's Posthumous Projects, 1980-1988 (Box 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Materials, 1934-2001 (Boxes 4-6 and 11; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1880-1990 (Boxes 6 and 11; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, 1918-1975 (Boxes 7-10 and 12-17; 2.2 linear feet)
Provenance
The papers of Fairfield Porter were given to the Archives of American Art by the artist's wife, Anne Porter, in five separate accessions between 1977 and 1997.
Location of Originals
Before donating the papers to the Archives, Anne Porter returned letters from Frank O'Hara to Fairfield Porter to the O'Hara estate. Letters from John Ashbery to Fairfield Porter were returned to Ashbery, and photocopies have been placed in the collection.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds an oral history of Fairfield Porter conducted by Paul Cummings in 1968.
Restrictions on Access
The bulk of this collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not digitized requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Fairfield Porter in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2006, and total 9600 images.
Brainard, Joe, 1942-; Burkhardt, Rudy; Button, John, 1929-1982; Day, Lucien B., 1916-; Downes, Rackstraw; Elmslie, Kenward; Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973; Frielicher, Jane; Giardelli, Arthur; Guest, Barbara; Hartl, Léon, 1889-; Hess, Thomas B.; Hirschl & Adler Galleries; Katz, Alex, 1927-; Koch, Kenneth, 1925-; Laning, Edward; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1997; Morse, Carl; Myers, John Bernard; O'Hara, Frank, 1926-1966; Padgett, Ron; Porter, Ruth W., 1875-1942; Rivers, Larry, 1925-; Schloss, Edith; Schuyler, James; Shapiro, David, 1947-; Stankiewicz, Richard, 1922-; Tibor de Nagy Gallery; Vasilieff, Nicholas; Art critics--New York (State)--Southampton; Lithographers--New York (State); Painters--New York (State)--Southampton; Painting, Modern--20th century; Photographs; Poets; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Travel diaries; Works of art
- Biographical Materials, 1916-1975 and undated; Series 1; (Box 1 and 11; 0.2 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical Materials include a chronology of Porter's life prepared by Prescott D. Schutz of Hirschl and Adler Gallery, a birth certificate, a diploma from Harvard College, various other certificates, two passports, a copy of Porter's will, bills and correspondence related to healthcare for the Porters' first son, Johnny, and writings by and about Porter's mother, Ruth Furness Porter. Also found is a copy of a letter from Porter's great-grandfather agreeing to the marriage of his daughter Margaret Eliot to James Furness.
  - Chronology of Fairfield Porter's Life (1981), undated; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates and Diplomas, 1929-1973; (see also Box 11, OV) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Passports, 1931-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fairfield Porter's Will (1961), undated; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Johnny Porter's Medical Records, 1944-1975; (not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Material Related to Ruth Furness Porter, James Furness, and Margaret Eliot Furness, 1916-1942, undated; (not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Certificates and Diplomas, (see Box 1, folder 2) (Box 11 (OV))
- Correspondence, 1918-1996 and undated; Series 2; (Boxes 1-2, 1.2 linear feet)
  Correspondence includes letters written by Fairfield Porter, Anne Porter, family members, artists, writers, critics, curators, neighbors, and others in Porter's circle. Incoming and outgoing letters are filed separately and arranged by correspondent. Single items of correspondence are filed in miscellaneous files by the first letter of the individual's last name. Incoming letters include letters to Fairfield and Anne Porter, as well as scattered third-party correspondence. Outgoing letters are mostly drafts and carbon copies of letters written by Fairfield Porter, although actual letters sent to his mother, wife, and Frank O'Hara are present.
  Significant correspondence is present from the Porters' many poet friends, including Kenneth Koch, James Schuyler, Ron Padgett, Kenward Elmslie, Barbara Guest, Carl Morse, David Shapiro, and others. Among the letters are poetry manuscripts by Koch, Morse, Schuyler, Padgett, and Shapiro. Some letters are actually written in verse, especially those from Kenneth Koch. See Writings for additional poetry manuscripts.
  Artists with letters in the collection include Joe Brainard, Rudy Burkhardt, John Button, Lucien Day, Rackstraw Downes, Philip Evergood, Jane Frielicher, Arthur Giardelli, Leon Hartl, Alex Katz, Edward Laning, Roy Lichtenstein, Larry Rivers, Richard Stankiewicz, Nicolas Vasilieff, among others. Other art world figures represented include John Bernard Myers, curator at the Tibor de Nagy gallery (New York), and Tom Hess, editor of ArtNews. Artwork found in this series includes an illustrated letter from Ron Padgett and an original print on a holiday card by Edith Schloss.
  Porter's interest in leftist politics during the 1930s is seen in outgoing letters and in letters from Alex Haberstroh and Paul Mattick. Letters to Porter's mother, Ruth Porter, contain detailed descriptions of his boarding school and college years and his travels abroad in the 1920s and 1930s.
  Annotations made by Anne Porter are found throughout this series, including dates, last names, and other explanatory notes.
  Additional correspondence can be found in Personal Business Records, especially among the gallery records, and in Anne Porter's Posthumous Projects. A collection of excerpts about Fairfield Porter, compiled by Anne Porter from letters she wrote to her mother, is filed with Writings by Others.
  - Incoming Letters to Anne and Fairfield Porter from: (Box 1)
    - Adams, Pat, 1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ashbery, John, undated; (photocopies of originals dated 1955-1973 and undated; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Auerbach, Ellen and Walter, 1939, 1942, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous A, 1957, 1981, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      (includes an undated letter from Peter Ackroyd and a 1981 letter from John Ashbery to Anne Porter)
    - Benedict, Michael, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Berend, Charlotte, 1952, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bergman, Joy, 1987-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bigelow, Don N., 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Birch, Barbara Channing, 1952, 1983-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bishop, Isabel, 1967-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Brainard, Joe, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Brooks, Jim, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Brown, Garrett Mills, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Buckley, Senator James L., 1971, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bullowa, Arthur, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Burkhardt, Rudy, 1951, 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Button, John, 1960-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous B, 1952-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
      (includes a 1989 postcard from Bill Berkson and a 1952 note from Louise Bourgeois)
    - Campbell, Larry, 1952, 1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Channing, Katherine M., 1933, 1942, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Clement, Adele, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Cornell, Joseph, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Cummings, E.E., 1946, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous C, 1942, 1965-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
      (includes a 1975 photo postcard from Dale Chihuly picturing him in Europe, and a 1966 letter from Oscar Collier)
    - Day, Lucien, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - DeMott, Benjamin, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Denby, Edwin, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Downes, Rackstraw, 1972-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous D, 1955-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
      (Includes a letter from James Deely)
    - Elmslie, Kenward, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Evergood, Philip, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous E, 1968-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Frazer, James, 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Freeman, Dick, 1972-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Freilicher, Jane, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous F, 1953-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
      (includes 1953 letter from John Ferren, a 1975 letter of condolence from Joe Fiore, and a 1956 letter from Jean Follett)
    - Giardelli, Arthur, 1936-1937, 1958-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Gilbert, Creighton, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Gordon, Albert, 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Griffin, Howard, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Guest, Barbara, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous G, 1952-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
      (includes a 1955 note from John Graham and a 1966 letter from Dorothy Grotz)
    - Haberstroh, Alex, 1935, 1939, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Hartl, Leon, 1952-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Hess, Tom, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous H, 1939-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Ickes, Betty, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Javits, Senator Jacob R., 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Johnson, Ben, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Katz, Alex, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Klein, Samuel and Pauline, 1967, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Koch, Katherine "Koko", 1982-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Koch, Kenneth, 1968-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Koethe, John, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Miscellaneous J, K, 1952-1978 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      (includes a brief 1968 note from Robert F. Kennedy, a 1960 note from William King, and a 1952 note from Doris Kreindler)
    - Laning, Edward, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Leake, Eugene W., 1966, 1968, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Leigh, Ted, 1972, 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Miscellaneous L, 1952-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
      (includes a 1954 letter from John C. LeClair, a 1994 letter from Denise Levertov, an undated letter from Roy Lichtenstein, a 1952 letter from Charles Locke and a 1963 letter from Tom Locker)
    - Maroger, Jacques, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Mattick, Ilse Hamm, undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Mattick, Paul, 1938-1941, undated; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 68-69)
    - Morse, Carl, 1970, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Myers, John Bernard, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Miscellaneous M, 1952-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
      (includes an undated letter from Dwight MacDonald, an undated letter from Norman MacLeish, an undated letter from John MacWhinnie, a 1952 note from Ezio Martinelli, a 1975 note from Harry Mathews, circa 1975 note from Peter Matthiessen, a 1963 note from Henry Mayer, and an undated note from Howard Moss)
    - Miscellaneous N, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - O'Hara, Frank, 1954, 1956, 1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Padgett, Ron, 1970-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Porter, Anne Channing (Box 1)
      - to Katherine M. Channing, 1936, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
      - to Fairfield Porter, circa 1934-1962; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 77-79)
    - Porter, Edward and Audrey, 1946-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Porter, Eliot and Aline, 1959-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Porter, John (Fairfield and Anne Porter's son), 1942-1968, 1977, undated; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 82-84)
    - Porter, John and Trudy, 1951-1956, 1970-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Porter, Ruth Furness, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Miscellaneous P, 1947-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
      (includes an undated letter from Harley Perkins and a 1947 letter to a family member from Miss Probst, Fairfield's German governess)
    - Rivers, Larry, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Miscellaneous Q-R, 1941-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 89)
      (includes a 1966 letter from Frank Redelius describing the prepartion of the Maroger Medium)
    - Schuyler, James, 1955-1989, undated; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 90-93)
    - Schloss, Edith, 1972-1996 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Shapiro, David, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Smith, Elizabeth, 1974-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Stankiewicz, Richard, 1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Straus, Francis, 1968, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Straus, Nancy Porter, 1952-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Miscellaneous S, 1956-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 100)
      (includes a 1969 letters from Robert G. Skinner, a 1956 postcard from David Smith, a 1956 letter from Raphael Soyer, and a 1970 note from Henry Striebel)
    - Tworkov, Jack, 1952, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Miscellaneous T, 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 102)
    - Vasilieff, Nicholas, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 103)
    - Walker, John, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 104)
    - Wallace, Frank, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - Welliver, Neil, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - White, Bobby, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 107)
    - Miscellaneous V, W, Y, 1955-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 108)
      (includes 1965 letter from Jean Volkmer concerning conservation of a Porter painting and a 1953 letter from Hudson Walker)
    - First Name Only, Albert, 1936, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 109)
    - Illegible and Unsigned Letters, 1952, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Outgoing Letters from Fairfield Porter to: (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous A, 1956, 1961; (draft and copy) (Box 1, Folder 111)
    - Channing, Katherine M. "Kee", 1935-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 112)
    - Miscellaneous F, 1918, 1923, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 113)
      (includes copy of a 1956 letter sent to Alfred Frankfurter and Betty Chamberlain)
    - Miscellaneous G-N, 1940-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 114)
      (includes drafts of letters to Clement Greenberg and Dwight MacDonald)
    - O'Hara, Frank, 1954-1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Porter, Anne, 1931-1964, undated; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
    - Porter, Ruth Furness, circa 1923-1942 and undated; (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 6-12)
    - Miscellaneous P, W, circa 1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - First Names Only, 1955, 1971, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Writings by Fairfield Porter, 1924-1975, undated; Series 3; (Box 2; 0.6 linear feet)